<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="fluid.usermanual"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>User Manual</title>

  <para>This chapter describes all things the users of the templating system
  needs to know. After you've read the introduction, you can dive into the
  concepts of Fluid which are relevant to you.</para>

  <para>The chapter starts with an overview of basic concepts, continues with
  using layouts, and finishes with how to write your own view helpers.</para>

  <section xml:id="fluid.usermanual.basicconcepts">
    <title>Basic concepts</title>

    <para>This section describes all basic concepts available.</para>

    <para>This includes:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Variables / Object Accessors</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>View Helpers</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Arrays</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <section>
      <title>Variables and Object Accessors</title>

      <para>A templating system would be quite pointless if it was not
      possible to display some external data in the templates. That's what
      variables are for:</para>

      <para>Suppose you want to output the title of your blog, you could write
      the following snippet into your controller:</para>

      <para><programlisting>$this-&gt;view-&gt;assign('blogTitle', $blog-&gt;getTitle());</programlisting>Then,
      you could output the blog title in your template with the following
      snippet:</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;h1&gt;This blog is called {blogTitle}&lt;/h1&gt;</programlisting>Now,
      you might want to extend the output by the blog author as well. To do
      this, you could repeat the above steps, but that would be quite
      inconvenient and hard to read. <footnote>
          <para>Remember: The semantics between the controller and the view
          should be the following: The controller says to the view "Please
          render the blog object I give to you", and not "Please render the
          Blog title, and the blog posting 1, ...". That's why passing objects
          to the view instead of simple values is highly encouraged.</para>
        </footnote></para>

      <para>That's why the template language has a special syntax for object
      access, demonstrated below. A nicer way of expressing the above is the
      following:</para>

      <para><programlisting><lineannotation>This should go into the controller:
</lineannotation>$this-&gt;view-&gt;assign('blog', $blog);
<lineannotation>This should go into the template:</lineannotation>
&lt;h1&gt;This blog is called <emphasis>{blog.title}</emphasis>, written by <emphasis>{blog.author}</emphasis>&lt;/h1&gt;</programlisting>Instead
      of passing strings to the template, we are passing whole objects around
      now - which is much nicer to use both from the controller and the view
      side. To access certain properties of these objects, you can use
      <emphasis>Object Accessors</emphasis>. By writing
      <code>{blog.title}</code>, the template engine will call a
      <code>getTitle()</code> method on the <code>blog</code> object, if it
      exists. Besides, you can use that syntax to traverse associative arrays
      and public properties.</para>

      <para><tip>
          <para>Deep nesting is supported: If you want to output the email
          address of the blog author, then you can use
          <code>{blog.author.email}</code>, which is roughly equivalent to
          <code>$blog-&gt;getAuthor()-&gt;getEmail()</code>.</para>
        </tip></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>View Helpers</title>

      <para>All output logic is placed in <emphasis>View
      Helpers</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>The view helpers are invoked by using XML tags in the template,
      and are implemented as PHP classes (more on that later).</para>

      <para>This concept is best understood with an example:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>Tags and Namespace declarations</title>

          <programlisting>{namespace f=TYPO3\Fluid\ViewHelpers}⁄<co
              xml:id="co.tags-example.1" />
&lt;f:link.action controller="Administration"&gt;Administration&lt;/f:link.action&gt;<co
              xml:id="co.tags-example.2" /></programlisting>

          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="co.tags-example.1">
              <para><emphasis>Namespace Declaration:</emphasis> You import the
              PHP Namespace <code>TYPO3\Fluid\ViewHelpers</code> under the prefix
              <code>f</code>. The above namespace import <code>{namespace
              f=TYPO3\Fluid\ViewHelpers}</code> is imported by default. All other
              namespaces need to be imported explicitely.<footnote>
                  <para>This is like an XML namespace import, just with a
                  different syntax.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="co.tags-example.2">
              <para>Calling the <emphasis>View Helper:</emphasis> The
              <code>&lt;f:link.action...&gt; ... &lt;/f:link.action&gt;</code>
              tag renders a link.</para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>

          <para>Now, the main difference between Fluid and other templating
          engines is how the view helpers are implemented: <emphasis>For each
          view helper, there exists a corresponding PHP class.</emphasis>
          Let's see how this works for the example above:</para>

          <para>The <code>&lt;f3:link.action /&gt;</code> tag is implemented
          in the class
          <classname>TYPO3\Fluid\ViewHelpers\Link\ActionViewHelper</classname>.</para>
        </example></para>

      <para>The class name of such a view helper is constructed for a given
      tag as follows:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The first part of the class name is the namespace which was
            imported (the namespace prefix f was expanded to its full
            namespace <code>TYPO3\Fluid\ViewHelpers</code>)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The unqualified name of the tag, without the prefix, is
            capitalized (<code>Link)</code>, and the postfix
            <code>ViewHelper</code> is appended.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>The tag and view helper concept is <emphasis>the core
      concept</emphasis> of Fluid. <emphasis>All output logic is implemented
      through such ViewHelpers / Tags!</emphasis> Things like
      <code>if/else</code>, <code>for</code>, ... are all implemented using
      custom tags - a main difference to other templating languages.</para>

      <para>Some benefits of this approach are:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You cannot override already existing view helpers by
            accident.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>It is very easy to write custom view helpers, which live
            next to the standard view helpers</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All user documentation for a view helper can be
            automatically generated from the annotations and code
            documentation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Most view helpers have some parameters. These can be plain
      strings, just like in <code>&lt;f:link.action
      controller="Administration"&gt;...&lt;/f:link.action&gt;</code>, but as
      well arbitary objects. Parameters of view helpers will just be parsed
      with the same rules as the rest of the template, thus you can pass
      arrays or objects as parameters.</para>

      <para>This is often used when adding arguments to links:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Creating a link with arguments</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;f:link.action controller="Blog" action="show" arguments="{singleBlog: blogObject}"&gt;... read more&lt;/f:link.action&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>Here, the view helper will get a parameter called
      <code>arguments</code> which is of type
      <emphasis>array</emphasis>.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>Make sure you <emphasis>do not put a space</emphasis> before or
        after the opening or closing brackets of an array. If you type
        <code>arguments=" {singleBlog : blogObject}"</code> (notice the space
        before the opening curly bracket), the array is automatically casted
        to a string (as a string concatenation takes place).</para>

        <para>This also applies when using object accessors:
        <code>&lt;f:do.something with="{object}" /&gt;</code> and
        <code>&lt;f:do.something with=" {object}" /&gt;</code> are
        substantially different: In the first case, the view helper will
        receive an <emphasis>object</emphasis> as argument, while in the
        second case, it will receive a <emphasis>string</emphasis> as
        argument.</para>

        <para>This might first seem like a bug, but actually it is just
        consistent that it works that way.</para>
      </warning>

      <section>
        <title>Boolean expressions</title>

        <para>Often, you need some kind of conditions inside your template.
        For them, you will usually use the <code>&lt;f:if&gt;</code>
        ViewHelper. Now let's imagine we have a list of blog postings and want
        to display some additional information for the currently selected blog
        posting. We assume that the currently selected blog is available in
        <code>{currentBlogPosting}</code>. Now, let's have a look how this
        works:</para>

        <example>
          <title>Using boolean expressions</title>

          <para><programlisting>&lt;f:for each="{blogPosts}" as="post"&gt;
  &lt;f:if condition="<emphasis>{post} == {currentBlogPosting}</emphasis>"&gt;... some special output here ...&lt;/f:if&gt; 
&lt;/f:for&gt;</programlisting></para>
        </example>

        <para>In the above example, there is a bit of new syntax involved:
        <code>{post} == {currentBlogPosting}</code>. Intuitively, this says
        "if the post I''m currently iterating over is the same as
        currentBlogPosting, do something."</para>

        <para>Why can we use this boolean expression syntax? Well, because the
        IfViewHelper has registered the argument <code>condition</code> as
        <code>boolean</code>. Thus, the boolean expression syntax is available
        in all arguments of ViewHelpers which are of type boolean.</para>

        <para>All boolean expressions have the form <emphasis>XX Comparator
        YY</emphasis>, where:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Comparator</emphasis> is one of the following:
            <emphasis>==, &gt;, &gt;=, &lt;, &lt;=, %</emphasis>
            (modulo)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>XX / YY</emphasis> is one of the following:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>A number (integer or float</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>A JSON Array</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>A ViewHelper</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>An Object Accessor (this is probably the most used
                example)</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Inline Notation for ViewHelpers</title>

        <para>In many cases, the tag-based syntax of ViewHelpers is really
        intuitive, especially when building loops, or forms. However, in other
        cases, using the tag-based syntax feels a bit awkward -- this can be
        demonstrated best with the
        <code>&lt;f:uri.resource&gt;</code>-ViewHelper, which is used to
        reference static files inside the <filename>Public/</filename> folder
        of a package. That's why it is often used inside
        <code>&lt;style&gt;</code> or <code>&lt;script&gt;</code>-tags,
        leading to the following code:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="&lt;f:uri.resource path='myCssFile.css' /&gt;" /&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>You will notice that this is really difficult to read, as two
        tags are nested into each other. That's where the inline notation
        comes into play: It allows the usage of
        <code>{f:uri.resource()}</code> instead of <code>&lt;f:uri.resource
        /&gt;</code>. The above example can be written like the
        following:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="{f:uri.resource(path:'myCssFile.css')}" /&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This is readable much better, and explains the intent of the
        ViewHelper in a much better way: It is used like a helper
        function.</para>

        <para>The syntax is still more flexible: In Real-World templates, you
        will often find code like the following, formatting a DateTime object
        (stored in <code>{post.date}</code> in the example below):</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;f:format.date format="d-m-Y"&gt;{post.date}&lt;/f:format.date&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This can also be re-written using the inline notation:</para>

        <programlisting>{post.date -&gt; f:format.date(format:'d-m-Y')}</programlisting>

        <para>This is also a lot better readable than the above syntax.</para>

        <tip>
          <para>This can also be nested indefinitely often, so one can write:
          <code>{post.date -&gt; foo:myHelper() -&gt; bar:bla()}</code></para>
        </tip>

        <para>To wrap it up: Internally, both syntax variants are handled
        equally, and every ViewHelper can be called in both ways. However, if
        the ViewHelper "feels" like a tag, use the tag-based notation, if it
        "feels" like a helper function, use the Inline Notation.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Arrays</title>

      <para>Some view helpers, like the <code>SelectViewHelper</code> (which
      renders an HTML select dropdown box), need to get associative arrays as
      arguments (mapping from internal to displayed name). See the following
      example how this works:</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;f:form.select options="{edit: 'Edit item', delete: 'Delete item'}" /&gt;</programlisting>The
      array syntax used here is very similar to the JSON object syntax. Thus,
      the left side of the associative array is used as key without any
      parsing, and the right side can be either:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>a number</para>

            <para><programlisting>{a : 1,
 b : 2
}</programlisting></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a string; Needs to be in either single- or double quotes. In
            a double-quoted string, you need to escape the " with a \ in front
            (and vice versa for single quoted strings). A string is again
            handled as Fluid Syntax, this is what you see in example c.</para>

            <para><programlisting>{a : 'Hallo',
 b : "Second string with escaped \" (double quotes) but not escaped ' (single quotes)"
 c : "{firstname} {lastname}"
}</programlisting></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a nested array</para>

            <para><programlisting>{a : {
    a1 : "bla1",
    a2 : "bla2"
  },
 b : "hallo"
}</programlisting></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a variable reference (=an object accessor)</para>

            <para><programlisting>{blogTitle : blog.title,
 blogObject: blog
}</programlisting></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="fluid.usermanual.passingdata">
    <title>Passing data to the view</title>

    <para>You can pass arbitary objects to the view, using
    <code>$this-&gt;view-&gt;assign(⁄<replaceable>IdentifierString</replaceable>,
    ⁄<replaceable>Object)</replaceable></code> from within the controller. See
    the above paragraphs about Object Accessors for details how to use the
    passed data.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="fluid.usermanual.layouts">
    <title>Layouts</title>

    <para>In almost all web applications, there are many similarities between
    each page. Usually, there are common templates or menu structures which
    will not change for many pages.</para>

    <para>To make this possible in Fluid, we created a layout system, which we
    will introduce in this section.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Writing a layout</title>

      <para>Every layout is placed in the
      <filename>Resources/Private/Layouts</filename> directory, and has the
      file ending <filename>.html</filename>. A layout is a normal Fluid
      template file, except there are some parts where the actual content of
      the target page should be inserted.</para>

      <example>
        <title>An example layout</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;&lt;title&gt;My fancy web application&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;div id="menu"&gt;... menu goes here ...&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="content"&gt;
  <emphasis>&lt;f:render section="content" /&gt;</emphasis><co
            xml:id="co.layout-example.1" />
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="co.layout-example.1">
            <para>With this tag, a section from the target template is
            rendered.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using a layout</title>

      <para>Using a layout involves two steps:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Declare which layout to use: <code>&lt;f:layout name="..."
            /&gt;</code> can be written anywhere on the page (though we
            suggest to write it on top, right after the namespace declaration)
            - the given name references the layout.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Provide the content for all sections used by the layout
            using the <code>&lt;f:section&gt;...&lt;/f:section&gt;</code> tag:
            <code>&lt;f:section
            name="content"&gt;...&lt;/f3:section&gt;</code></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>For the above layout, a minimal template would look like the
      following:</para>

      <example>
        <title>A template for the above layout</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;f:layout name="example.html" /&gt;

&lt;f:section name="content"&gt;
<replaceable>This HTML here will be outputted to inside the layout</replaceable>
&lt;/f:section&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="fluid.usermanual.writingaviewhelper">
    <title>Writing your own View Helper</title>

    <para>As we have seen before, <emphasis>all output logic resides in View
    Helpers</emphasis>. This includes the standard control flow operators such
    as <code>if/else</code>, HTML forms, and much more. This is the concept
    which makes Fluid extremely versatile and extensible.</para>

    <para>If you want to create a view helper which you can call from your
    template (as a tag), you just write a plain PHP class which needs to
    inherit from <classname>TYPO3\Fluid\Core\AbstractViewHelper</classname> (or
    its subclasses). You need to implement only one method to write a view
    helper:</para>

    <para><methodname>public function render()</methodname></para>

    <section>
      <title>Rendering the View Helper</title>

      <para>We refresh what we have learned so far: When a user writes
      something like <code>&lt;blog:displayNews /&gt;</code> inside a template
      (and has imported the "blog" namespace to
      <classname>TYPO3\Blog\ViewHelpers</classname>), Fluid will automatically
      instanciate the class
      <classname>TYPO3\Blog\ViewHelpers\DisplayNewsViewHelper</classname>, and
      invoke the <methodname>render()</methodname> method on it.</para>

      <para>This <methodname>render()</methodname> method should return the
      rendered content as string.</para>

      <para>You have the following possibilities to access the environment
      when rendering your view helper:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>$this-&gt;arguments</code> is a read-only associative
            array where you will find the values for all arguments you
            registered previously.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><code>$this-&gt;renderChildren()</code> renders everything
            between the opening and closing tag of the view helper and returns
            the rendered result (as string).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><code>$this-&gt;templateVariableContainer</code> is an
            instance of
            <classname>TYPO3\Fluid\Core\ViewHelper\TemplateVariableContainer</classname>,
            with which you have access to all variables currently available in
            the template.</para>

            <para>Additionally, you can add variables to the container with
            <code>$this-&gt;templateVariableContainer-&gt;add($identifier,
            $value)</code>, but you have to make sure that you
            <emphasis>remove every variable you added</emphasis> again! This
            is a security measure against side-effects.</para>

            <para>It is also not possible to add a variable to the
            TemplateVariableContainer if a variable of the same name already
            exists - again to prevent side effects and scope problems.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Now, we will look at an example: How to write a view helper giving
      us the <code>foreach</code> functionality of PHP.<footnote>
          <para>This view helper is already available in the standard library
          as <code>&lt;f:for&gt;..&lt;/f:for&gt;</code>. We still use it as
          example here, as it is quite simple and shows many
          possibilities.</para>
        </footnote></para>

      <example>
        <title>Implementing a loop</title>

        <para>A loop could be called within the template in the following
        way:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;f:for each="{blogPosts}" as="blogPost"&gt;
  &lt;h2&gt;{blogPost.title}&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/f:for&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>So, in words, what should the loop do?</para>

        <para>It needs two arguments:<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><code>each</code>: Will be set to some
              <emphasis>object</emphasis><footnote>
                  <para>Remember that the view helper can receive arbitary
                  objects as parameters!</para>
                </footnote> which can be iterated over.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><code>as</code>: The <emphasis>name</emphasis> of a
              variable which will contain the current element being iterated
              over</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>

        <para>It then should do the following (in pseudocode):<programlisting>foreach ($each as $$as) {
  // render everything between opening and closing tag
}</programlisting></para>

        <para>Implementing this is fairly straightforward, as you will see
        right now:</para>

        <programlisting>class ForViewHelper {
  /**
   * Renders a loop
   *
   * @param array $each Array to iterate over<co xml:id="co.forViewHelper.1" />
   * @param string $as Iteration variable
   */
  public function render(array $each, $as) {<co xml:id="co.forViewHelper.2" />
    $out = '';
    foreach ($each as $singleElement) {
      $this-&gt;variableContainer-&gt;add($as, $singleElement);
      $out .= $this-&gt;renderChildren();<co xml:id="co.forViewHelper.3" />
      $this-&gt;variableContainer-&gt;remove($as);
    }
    return $out;
  }
}</programlisting>

        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="co.forViewHelper.1">
            <para>The PHPDoc <emphasis>is part of the code</emphasis>! Fluid
            extracts the argument datatypes from the PHPDoc.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="co.forViewHelper.2">
            <para>You can simply register arguments to the view helper by
            adding them as method arguments of the
            <methodname>render()</methodname> method.</para>
          </callout>

          <callout arearefs="co.forViewHelper.3">
            <para>Here, everything between the opening and closing tag of the
            view helper is rendered and returned as string.</para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>

        <para>The above example demonstrates how we add a variable, render all
        children (everything between the opening and closing tag), and remove
        the variable again to prevent side-effects.</para>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Declaring arguments</title>

      <para>We have now seen that we can add arguments just by adding them as
      method arguments to the <methodname>render()</methodname> method. There
      is, however, a second method to register arguments:</para>

      <para>You can also register arguments inside a method called
      <methodname>initializeArguments()</methodname>. Call
      <code>$this-&gt;registerArgument(<replaceable>$name</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>$dataType</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>$description</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>$isRequired</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>$defaultValue</replaceable>=NULL)</code> inside.</para>

      <para>It depends how many arguments a view helper has. Sometimes,
      registering them as render() arguments is more beneficial, and sometimes
      it makes more sense to register them in
      <methodname>initializeArguments()</methodname>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>AbstractTagBasedViewHelper</title>

      <para>Many view helpers output an HTML tag - for example
      <code>&lt;f3:link.action ...&gt; outputs </code>a <code>&lt;a
      href="..."&gt;</code> tag. There are many ViewHelpers which work that
      way.</para>

      <para>Very often, you want to add a CSS class or a target attribute to
      an <code>&lt;a href="..."&gt;</code> tag. This often leads to repetitive
      code like below. (Don't look at the code too thoroughly, it should just
      demonstrate the boring and repetitive task one would have without the
      AbstractTagBasedViewHelper).<programlisting>class LinkViewHelper extends \TYPO3\Fluid\Core\AbstractViewHelper {
  public function initializeArguments() {
    $this-&gt;registerArgument('class', 'string', 'CSS class to add to the link');
    $this-&gt;registerArgument('target', 'string', 'Target for the link');
    ... and more ...
  }
  public function render() {
    $output = '&lt;a href="..."';
    if ($this-&gt;arguments['class']) {
      $output .= ' class="' . $this-&gt;arguments['class'] . '"';
    }
    if ($this-&gt;arguments['target']) {
      $output .= ' target="' . $this-&gt;arguments['target'] . '"';
    }
    $output .= '&gt;';
    ... and more ...
    return $output;
  }
}</programlisting></para>

      <para>Now, the AbstractTagBasedViewHelper introduces two more methods
      you can use inside <code>initializeArguments()</code>:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>registerTagAttribute($name, $type, $description,
            $required)</code>: Use this method to register an attribute which
            should be directly added to the tag</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><code>registerUniversalTagAttributes()</code>: If called,
            registers the standard HTML attributes (class, id, dir, lang,
            style, title).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Inside the AbstractTagBasedViewHelper, there is a TagBuilder
      object available (with <code>$this-&gt;tag</code>) which makes building
      a tag a lot more straightforward</para>

      <para>With the above methods we get, the <code>LinkViewHelper</code>
      from above can be condensed as follows:<programlisting>class LinkViewHelper extends \TYPO3\Fluid\Core\AbstractViewHelper {
	public function initializeArguments() {
		$this-&gt;registerUniversalTagAttributes();
	}

	/**
	 * Render the link.
	 *
	 * @param string $action Target action
	 * @param array $arguments Arguments
	 * @param string $controller Target controller. If NULL current controllerName is used
	 * @param string $package Target package. if NULL current package is used
	 * @param string $subpackage Target subpackage. if NULL current subpackage is used
	 * @param string $section The anchor to be added to the URI
	 * @return string The rendered link
	 */
	public function render($action = NULL, array $arguments = array(), $controller = NULL, $package = NULL, $subpackage = NULL, $section = '') {
		$uriBuilder = $this-&gt;controllerContext-&gt;getURIBuilder();
		$uri = $uriBuilder-&gt;URIFor($action, $arguments, $controller, $package, $subpackage, $section);
		$this-&gt;tag-&gt;addAttribute('href', $uri);
		$this-&gt;tag-&gt;setContent($this-&gt;renderChildren());

		return $this-&gt;tag-&gt;render();
	}
}</programlisting></para>

      <para>Additionally, we now already have support for all universal HTML
      attributes.</para>

      <para>You might now think that the building blocks are ready, but there
      is one more nice thing to add: <code>additionalAttributes</code>! Read
      about it in the next section.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>The TagBasedViewHelper also makes sure that all attributes are
        escaped properly, so to decrease the risk of Cross-Site Scripting
        attacks, make sure to use it when building tags.</para>
      </tip>

      <section>
        <title>additionalAttributes</title>

        <para>Sometimes, you need some HTML attributes which are not part of
        the standard. As an example: if you use the Dojo JavaScript framework,
        using these non-standard attributes makes life a lot easier.<footnote>
            <para>There are always some religious discussions whether to allow
            non-standard attributes or not. People being against it argue that
            it "pollutes" HTML, and makes it not validate anymore. More
            pragmatic people see some benefits to custom attributes in some
            contexts: If you use JavaScript to evaluate them, they will be
            ignored by the rendering engine if JavaScript is switched off, and
            can enable special behavior when JavaScript is turned on. Thus,
            they can make it easy to provide degradable interfaces.</para>

            <para>(Before bashing Dojo now: Of course you do not
            <emphasis>need</emphasis> the additional HTML arguments, but they
            make work with it a lot more comfortable)</para>
          </footnote>We think that the templating framework should not
        constrain the user in his possibilities - thus, it should be possible
        to add custom HTML attributes as well, if they are needed (People who
        have already worked with JSP know that it can be difficult to archive
        this. Our solution looks as follows:</para>

        <para><emphasis>Every view helper which inherits from
        <code>AbstractTagBasedViewHelper</code> has a special property called
        <code>additionalAttributes</code> which allows you to add arbitary
        HTML attributes to the tag.</emphasis></para>

        <para><code>additionalAttributes</code> should be an associative
        array, where the key is the name of the HTML attribute.</para>

        <para>If the link tag from above needed a new attribute called
        <code>fadeDuration</code>, which is not part of HTML, you could do
        that as follows:<programlisting>&lt;f:link.action ... additionalAttributes="{fadeDuration : 800}"&gt;Link with fadeDuration set&lt;/f:link.action&gt;</programlisting></para>

        <para>This attribute is available in all tags that inherit from
        <classname>TYPO3\Fluid\Core\ViewHelper\AbstractTagBasedViewHelper</classname>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>AbstractConditionViewHelper</title>

      <para>If you want to build some kind of if/else condition, you should
      base the ViewHelper on the <code>AbstractConditionViewHelper</code>, as
      it gives you convenient methods to render the <emphasis>then</emphasis>
      or <emphasis>else</emphasis>-parts of a ViewHelper. Let's look at the
      <code>&lt;f:if&gt;</code>-ViewHelper for a usage example, which should
      be quite self-explanatory:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;?php
class IfViewHelper extends \TYPO3\Fluid\Core\ViewHelper\AbstractConditionViewHelper {

	/**
	 * renders &lt;f:then&gt; child if $condition is true, otherwise renders &lt;f:else&gt; child.
	 *
	 * @param boolean $condition View helper condition
	 * @return string the rendered string
	 * @author Sebastian Kurfürst &lt;sebastian@typo3.org&gt;
	 * @author Bastian Waidelich &lt;bastian@typo3.org&gt;
	 * @api
	 */
	public function render($condition) {
		if ($condition) {
			return $this-&gt;renderThenChild();
		} else {
			return $this-&gt;renderElseChild();
		}
	}
}
?&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>By basing your condition ViewHelper on the
      <code>AbstractConditionViewHelper</code>, you will get the following
      features:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Two API methods <methodname>renderThenChild()</methodname> and
          <methodname>renderElseChild()</methodname>, which should be used in
          the then / else case.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The ViewHelper will have two arguments defined, called
          <code>then</code> and <code>else</code>, which are very helpful in
          the Inline Notation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The ViewHelper will automatically work with the
          <code>&lt;f:then&gt;</code> and
          <code>&lt;f:else&gt;</code>-Tags.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Widgets</title>

    <para>Widgets are special ViewHelpers which encapsulate complex
    functionality. It can be best understood what widgets are by giving some
    examples:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>&lt;f:widget.paginate&gt;</code> renders a Paginator, i.e.
        can be used to display large amounts of objects. This is best known
        from search engines.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>&lt;f:widget.autocomplete&gt;</code> adds autocompletion
        functionality to a text field.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>More widgets could include a Google Maps widget, a sortable
        grid, ...</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Internally, widgets consist of an own Controller and View
    part.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Using Widgets</title>

      <para>Using widgets inside your templates is really simple: Just use
      them like standard ViewHelpers, and consult their documentation for
      usage examples. An example for the
      <code>&lt;f:widget.paginate&gt;</code> follows below:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;f:widget.paginate itemsPerPage="10" objects="{blogs}" as="paginatedBlogs"&gt;
  // use {paginatedBlogs} as you used {blogs} before, most certainly inside
  // a &lt;f:for&gt; loop.
&lt;/f:widget.paginate&gt;
</programlisting>

      <para> In the above example, it looks like {blogs} contains all Blog
      objects, thus you might wonder if all objects were fetched from the
      database. However, the blogs are NOT fetched from the database until you
      actually use them, so the paginate ViewHelper will adjust the query sent
      to the database and receive only the small subset of objects. So, there
      is no negative performance overhead in using the Paginate Widget.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Writing widgets</title>

      <para>We already mentioned that a widget consists of a controller and a
      view, all triggered by a ViewHelper. We'll now explain these different
      components one after each other, explaining the API you have available
      for creating your own widgets.</para>

      <section>
        <title>ViewHelper</title>

        <para>All widgets inherit from
        <classname>TYPO3\Fluid\Core\Widget\AbstractWidgetViewHelper</classname>.
        The ViewHelper of the widget is the main entry point; it controls the
        widget and sets necessary configuration for the widget.</para>

        <para>To implement your own widget, the following things need to be
        done:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The controller of the widget needs to be injected into the
            <varname>$controller</varname> property.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Inside the <methodname>render()</methodname>-method, you
            should call <code>$this-&gt;initiateSubRequest()</code>, which
            will initiate a request to the controller which is set in the
            <varname>$controller</varname> property, and return the
            <classname>Response</classname> object.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>By default, all ViewHelper arguments are stored as
        <emphasis>Widget Configuration</emphasis>, and are also available
        inside the Widget Controller. However, to modify the Widget
        Configuration, you can override the
        <methodname>getWidgetConfiguration()</methodname> method and return
        the configuration which you need there.</para>

        <para>There is also a property <varname>$ajaxWidget</varname>, which
        we will explain later in the section "Ajax Widgets".</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Controller</title>

        <para>A widget contains one controller, which must inherit from
        <classname>TYPO3\Fluid\Core\Widget\AbstractWidgetController</classname>,
        which is an <classname>ActionController</classname>. There is only one
        difference between the normal ActionController which you are used to,
        and the <classname>AbstractWidgetController</classname>, which is the
        property <varname>$widgetConfiguration</varname>, containing the
        Widget's configuration which was set in the ViewHelper.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Fluid Template</title>

        <para>The Fluid templates of a widget are normal Fluid templates as
        you know them, but have a few ViewHelpers available additionally,
        which are described below:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>&lt;f:uri.widget&gt;</code>: Generates an URI to
            another action of the widget.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><code>&lt;f:link.widget&gt;</code>: Generates a link to
            another action of the widget.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><code>&lt;f:renderChildren&gt;</code>: Can be used to render
            the child nodes of the Widget ViewHelper, possibly with some more
            variables declared.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Ajax Widgets</title>

        <para>Widgets have special support for AJAX functionality. We'll first
        explain what needs to be done to create an AJAX compatible widget, and
        then explain it with an example.</para>

        <para>To make a widget AJAX-aware, you need to do the
        following:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>set <varname>$ajaxWidget</varname> to <code>TRUE</code>
            inside the ViewHelper. This will generate an unique AJAX
            Identifier for the Widget, and store the WidgetConfiguration in
            the user's session on the server.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Inside the <code>index</code>-action of the Widget
            Controller, generate the JavaScript which triggers the AJAX
            functionality. There, you will need a URI which returns the AJAX
            response. For that, use <code>&lt;f:uri.widget ajax="TRUE"
            action="..." arguments="..." /&gt;</code> inside the
            template.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Inside the template of the AJAX request,
            <code>&lt;f:renderChildren&gt;</code> is not available, because
            the child nodes of the Widget ViewHelper are not accessible
            there.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="ViewHelperLibrary.xml" />
</chapter>
